in the end the the beautiful thing about
Market making is it's very Democratic
and like if you aren't making the
markets better you don't get to trade so
you know there's would you be able to
help our viewers on a channel understand
what Market making is and how firms
primarily make money out of Market
making activities I've been in the same
kind of market for a long time I've been
I've seen you know from the days of
trading on sheets in the pit to the
things now I mean would you be willing
to say what the minimum salary that
you've seen in the industry for someone
who's first starting out all the way
into there there is theoretically Edge
and trade um but the the margin for
error is insanely small people making
directional bets are usually your best
friend uh they aren't playing so in
options you know they're not playing
volatility they're playing Direction
well okay I can easily H Direction risk
and it's incredibly interesting to see
like some of the most successful firms
today how close they came to closing
down like the number of firms that are
are gigantic today that that have came
within a hair of feeling what advice
would you give um to young people what
differentiates a candidate getting in
and what would you recommend to aspiring
you know so getting the actual
application of the way markets work uh
to combine that with a theory is where a
lot of people run into trouble know that
this industry changes so fast um this
actually has bitten me a couple times in
my career you become really successful
and you you kind of like rest on your
laurels uh but
like if you're not constantly innovating
constantly changing you get left behind
so fast so just always always always be
pushing always be
curious
so welcome back to the Quant insights uh
second podcast here we have a guest who
wants to remain anonymous today but has
20 years of experience um Market making
for different firms and he's going to be
referred to as John today John Smith so
John hey great to have you on the
podcast would you be able to explain a
little bit of your Market making
experience and how you got into the
space and your career development today
yeah of course uh thanks for having me
um so I got into options making Market
making 20 years ago um actually applied
to a firm out of school I had no idea
what I wanted to do but I had a computer
science degree and decided that a
cubicle was not for me and so this
seemed somewhat appealing uh went to the
firm I traded in the pit for a number of
years uh eventually started um traded on
my own for a long time and then and now
I'm back to working for firms again um
just to be generic but uh I've been in
the same kind of market for a long time
I've been I've seen you know from the
days of trading on sheets in the pit to
the things now I mean from markets that
are 20x wider than then than they are
now things are hundreds of times faster
now than they were then so it's it's
been a wild ride a lot of changes that's
really interesting what would you say is
the biggest difference um between the
changes then when you're trading in the
pits and you're saying markets are so
wide was there more opportunity then or
is there more opportunity now it's just
different um there's a lot more volume
now and the pricing now is so much
better like back then you you you know
you you weren't able to put things in as
fast you weren't able to run your your
smiles as fast so like you're trading
off sheets and you might have something
worth five and it's trading nine uh and
you know so you like you know and try to
adjust your sheets in your head so like
there's just a more margin for error uh
and I like to tell people yeah like
things used to be a dollar wide so if
you were you know if you were wrong it
you had a lot of room for error now if
you're off by a dime you're on the wrong
side back then if you're oh I have 90
cents of Edge and this isad of a dollar
now you now you sold it instead of
buying it um and then like things just
happen a lot faster you know in the pit
people have to physically ask you for
quotes and so you're always uh you know
you're on top of it and you can change
it you know different markets you can
update quickly but like now with the
screens like you you are vulnerable
every you know you have potentially tens
of thousands of markets out there at the
same time and you know you got to be on
top of things a little bit and there's
no one telling you oh hey you're off on
this they tell you you're off on that by
trading it with you so obviously a big
difference to having all those screens
in front of you now with um all inhouse
propri Tre trading software that makes
looking at all that data you know
visually in an easy way well I guess um
taking it Taking It From the Start would
you be able to help our viewers on a
channel understand what Market making is
and how firms primarily make money out
of Market Mak activities oh sure
absolutely um so I work as an options
Market maker and what we basically do is
you have a theoretical value and then
you will vend to the market via
computers or voice uh bids and asks um
you know so you're willing to buy or
sell everything uh one-sided markets are
very frowned upon um and then you know
you try to incorporate enough Edge into
your spread such that you will make
money over the long run you will
probably make money on more trades than
you lose on um but you tend to lose more
money on the ones when you're wrong uh
be
it uh someone knows something you don't
or uh if you're slow like if your
systems aren't fast and the underlying
moves and you're the last one to move
you you can get ripped on on Delta and
then you know you throw away your whole
days worth of profits on one trade so
like it's a there there's theoretically
Edge in every trade um but the the
margin for error is insanely small so
and and that's that's coming about by
informed Traders so if I if I run that
back you're you're trying to be there on
both the bid um and the ask and then
you're trying to make that difference
but then at the end of the day of course
you end up holding a position because
they're are informed Traders um who who
who are in the market and they're trying
to be directional so you end up with a
position and I guess what what
percentage of the time have you seen it
over your career that firms are wanting
to hedge um those directional positions
that then you have to take on um versus
uh you know actually hold a position on
your book
oh I mean like you're you're going like
you'll try to keep your your Greeks as
neutral as you can unless you have an
opinion right uh directional risk is the
easiest one to hedge you know you just
get out and hedge there then you know
your V risk and your interest rate risk
and your skew and your Curt and uh all
your teenies are where you really run
into problems um
but dire so in Market making um people
making directional bets are usually your
best friend uh they aren't playing so in
options you know they're not playing
volatility they're playing Direction
well okay I can easily hedge Direction
risk so you know I sell you a call and I
buy Futures and I hope you win because
then you're going to come back and get
out of the market and I'm going to get
Edge back again uh but people are
actually trading volatility right so
someone trades a straddle or something
like that um if you know I don't know
how knowledgeable people are listening
to this a straddle would be an at the
money call and an at the money put
together so generally a bet on movement
either more or less but those people are
actually making a bet that you're
probably going to win or lose on you
know you can't hedge away that risk
unless you have other well you try to by
selling other options or buying other
options but generally they're actually
making it bet against you where's the
directional guy and and you can make
them just be
friends exactly so that that's actually
quite interesting so you brought up a
almost volatility um trading strategy
there and you're you're just explaining
that it's a bit of a zero sum game with
the market maker um I I would put a
caveat to that are how many market
makers are on the exact same product you
know for example um if if I'm doing a
trade with two legs there and I'm trying
to execute as a retail Trader am I
guaranteed to have the same Market maker
be on both sides of that trade no I mean
ideally you almost aren't um so say most
markets uh call it 12 to 18 market
makers uh all you know well backed and
things like that so like in general as a
as a retail Trader you would want I mean
you guess you want everyone there and
have it be super tight but in general if
two market makers disagree so that one
guy's a little better bid and one guy a
little better offer that makes for a
tighter market for you um I mean you can
it depends what markets are uh most
products that I'm aware of no one's
really over 25% market share so you're
going to be trading with more than one
person uh but it would be the same group
of people every time excellent so so if
if we have 12 market makers on the same
um on the same line and they're all
trying to compete for the business I
guess the the obvious question is what
what's in it for them so yes they're
going after this difference in bit ass
spread and um they're willing to take on
positional risk as a part of that and
take on all these other risks um you
know gamma and Theta risk and things
like that but what's what's the primary
incentive for
them I mean you're trying to maximize
Edge while minimizing risk um
so in the end the the beautiful thing
about Market making is it's very
Democratic and like if you aren't making
the markets better you don't get to
trade so you know there's
I payment for order flow aside um so the
more aggressive market makers are the
tighter markets become for retail
Traders and if you want to be successful
in Market making you markets get tighter
every year they will continue to get
tighter every year um so like yeah like
you're basically trying to balance you
want to be on the trade um but you don't
want to get run over on the trade so
like
say the Market's a bucket a buck 10
right and you're like okay I really want
to sell this well say it's price time
you can offer A110 but you're behind
other people or you can offer a doll
five but maybe that's not enough Edge
for you to like compensate for your risk
so you're just trying to balance out you
know making as as much money as you can
while uh I guess being in the market
like if you you're like oh I'm if the
Market's a buck a buck five and you're
90 cents at 110 you're just not going to
trade so like it's it's a balancing act
of of getting on the trades you want to
get on trying to avoid the other trades
but like appropriately charging for risk
I guess is the main the main idea that
makes a lot of sense and at what at what
point on a specific product I mean I
guess there's all different kind of risk
limits but is it usually a volumetric
limit um that's being run real time that
you know a market maker would be willing
to have on a particular product at a
particular tenure um at a particular
strike to actually um take directionally
on their book oh sure I mean so all
market makers will have different risk
limits but to my knowledge all market
makers have risk at least internal uh
but like yeah you would you know you
have X amount of Vega risk you could
take x amount of theta uh the big one is
what would call span risk right like I I
don't want to lose more than x dollars
on a 3sd move and mean you'll know too
like a 3sd move in options is not really
a 3sd move right like it's they happen
way more than they of course yeah I mean
I mean you've brought up span there so
is this a daily process that your rist
team will run and make you guys aware of
um you know do they run the span the
span book or is that going on ongoing
during the day during the trading day
yeah that's second by second and like
different risks you you'll have
different like um time frames to cover
different risks like maybe you're okay
with this risk but you don't want to go
home with it right so like maybe like by
the end of the day like a lot of times
when we were doing our own thing um like
okay we have this span risk and it's not
an emergency right because the markets
are open um when markets are closed it's
a lot riskier because they can Gap a lot
easier um so you're like okay I want to
cover this before I go home but
sometimes you'll have just a gigantic
amount like say you sold a bunch of
calls and you have actual Deltas you're
like okay I need to get these done in
the next 30 seconds so like different
risks have different time frames um But
like everyone kind of has these limits
that they're trying to stay under um
everyone you know that's that's another
big source
of uh I don't know people still working
on like what what is the right amount of
risk and every firm's different too uh
you know different firms have different
like risk reward profiles they're
looking for some firms are willing to
take a lot more risk than others some
groups are taking will to take a lot
more risk than others some people just
want to you know Harvest bit ask and
have a high sharp and some people are
willing to forego sharp for more money
uh or the opportunity for more money and
in in that opportunity um I I would
imagine of course even just speaking
about different um different ways that
you may trade volatility um as a market
maker that different strategies present
different risk reward benefits so you
know if if you have a volumetric risk
directionally on a um on a certain
product um Let It Be You Know strike and
in time but then does that actually
present difficulties when looking at the
portfolio as a whole because you may
have actually traded off some of that
risk by um you know doing a multi-legged
strategy how do how is that balanced on
the risk book or is it always a
volumetric uh limit per per product no I
mean so it all it all goes into the same
soup um
in a large derivatives Market making
book you're going to
have got honestly maybe hundreds of
thousands of strikes on um so you just
it it's you know you're like okay that
has this much Vega this much skew this
much Curt and it just kind of goes into
the soup and then you you would want to
look at like okay what's my Vega right
here but also what's my Vega on a move
um those kind of things um so yeah
you're just kind of trying to handle
like things like that obviously like the
so you know in generic options par a
straddle would be very risky a spread
like a bull spread call Spread putot
spread be less risky and then a
butterfly would be less risky than that
you you constantly want to be liking
butterfly right so like if you have a
call spread position on your longer call
spread then you'd want to uh like sell a
further out call spread then you have
the butterfly like you basically can
mitigate a lot of your risk by
tightening things up on the V smile like
basically you want things to be as close
as possible like
your 45 Del to call and your 40 Del to
call are very related whereas your 10
Del to put and your five Del to call um
are not as related um again I I
apologize I'm getting specific there but
your meteor options versus your further
away options kind of thing no no that's
that's that's great Insight so yeah and
and um so Market making activities
around options specifically so when you
are covering so many products over
different times and um and different
different durations different stripes
and possibly different products and
underlines completely and you've got one
market making person um sitting on the
same thing what kind of software are
they using and what are they looking at
are they looking at a volatility smile
to help them trade sure so at this point
it's almost all proprietary
um there are a few vended softwares out
there uh that like you could use if you
want to like look at risk and things
like that but they're generally not fast
enough to compete with uh the firm's
proprietary stuff these days but I mean
we
had six screams just full and like
you're still fighting for scream St so
you've got your smile up got your term
structure up you got the B on the day
you know you're looking at 16 different
things and then you get you know your
actual markets um opportunities in the
market um other other things like you
know so if you're trading oil you might
want to keep an eye on gold and the S&P
that kind of thing so it's really hard
like you kind of get used to it but it's
kind of overwhelming at first you're
like oh there's 50 things that I'm going
to watch right now but there typically
you just kind of make a rotation through
them and and in your experience you know
20 years being on the desk you would
have seen a lot of Juniors come into
this position um from the start I guess
what what are some of the challenges
that a junior Market maker has when they
first come on the desk but you know
they've just freshly come out of
University they know all the math um
they're really switched on maybe they
can do a little bit of programming what
are the main challenges that someone
like that faces when they first get into
the real world and they're trading an
option
book sure I mean one of the biggest
things is that the people coming into
the industry now are just smarter than
they used to be uh the competition for
these jobs is is a lot harder I'm not
sure that I would get past a resume pile
uh these days but a lot of them I mean
these people are brilliant um and
they've had success their whole lives
and most things have probably been easy
and this is a very unique industry uh
there aren't really books out there you
can't really prepare yourself for for
Market making you just to have to figure
it out once you get there you know it's
kind of
pass down um I'm sure one day there will
be uh but you know so getting the actual
application of the way markets work uh
to combine that with a theory is where a
lot of people run into trouble you know
the the situations the market mechanics
you know
like things don't have one price uh they
have Sol prices you know there's a bid
and an ask and if you want to buy it you
can't necessarily buy the bid maybe you
can maybe you can't maybe you can get it
done from bid maybe you have to pay the
offer um trading costs matter a lot uh
you know the things trade like oh I
would have traded that like yeah but
like you know we missed it so now we to
figure out why we missed it like we're
taking earlier like it's you have to be
very careful with your quotes out there
and so in the theoretical world like you
get these people um who are just like I
said just brilliant uh and they can do
all the math and they there's a place
for that in the theoretical Quant as
well but for your Quant Traders you also
have to understand the way the markets
actually work and that's kind of where
people get frustrated um and it takes a
long time you know um when I came into
this industry I like to tell people like
it took me six months before I even knew
what I did for a living uh just just
kind of getting used to it um but yeah
it's just it's hard and there's you know
these people are used to be able to
study things and there's not books for
it so you just kind of have to like
figure it out uh and and some people it
comes easy and some people it doesn't
most people can if you love it if you
really really love it you can generally
get there um but it's just a a different
world I guess it's it's very different
than
Academia yeah I can I can imagine that
there's a bit of a training will period
um with the actual Traders coming onto
the desk and a big big learning curve of
how the markets work um and interesting
to see um maybe some of it and most of
it is in that execution of the actual
trading book um and then knowing what
your costs are going to be and that you
can't necessarily trade at your bid and
offer all the time um but uh yeah moving
more into that and the experience that
someone needs what would you recommend
um for a person coming in knowing what
those challenges are are there any
resources or opportunities that you
would recommend to a person coming in
who's um trying to be the best Market
maker that they can possibly
be um sure I mean like you know your
Basics your your probability statistics
your coding your linear algebra um all
going to be first and foremost for like
just kind of knowledge uh for resources
Honestly YouTube is is quite good uh I
can think of at least one channel I know
it's pretty strong for Quant uh python
stuff um but
like in general the best way to learn
trading in
my my opinion I guess is to trade um
paper trade cash trade small money or
something like that but get get in the
market trade your personal money see how
you do like you know uh there there's
simulations too where I think you could
simulate a market maker strategy it's
hard to it's probably harder to simulate
a market strategy but you can get used
to the things like expiration risk and
things like that people have a hard time
with that you know everyone I remember
we
had uh Quant start uh when we were on
our own and you know they just don't
really understand the in like oh well
volatility you sold volatility and then
volatility went lower so you should have
made money and you're like well no
because we also moved a lot and there's
a lot of ins and outs of things that
like you you kind of get a feel for
there like otherwise you would just
always sell things if if you didn't lose
money when you moved like you would
always sell every option um you so you
can be directionally right with your
volatility but if your timing's off then
maybe you're not making money fast
enough yeah yeah like yeah like or like
you see a lot of this on um on numbers
right or like economic data so like when
the unemployment data comes out
volatility will go lower but also you'll
probably move so you you know your p&l
has a lot to do with both of those
things um like oh you sold a 15 ball and
now it's a 13 Ball but you moved 4% like
so you lost a lot of money because what
you're short doesn't even have all let's
Okay so say you short an at the money
option but you move so far that it
becomes a 10 Delta option now like your
sensitivity to that parameter is not
what it
was um so like a lot of this stuff that
like you don't really get a feel for in
a class or or with software like you
know um the the real application of it
it just it it's not totally necessary
but man does it help with intuition when
you get those quants who actually
understand the ins and outs of Market
mechanics and trading they those are the
people who are going to run these firms
someday um the people who can put
together like an actual trading idea
with the math and the the coding it it's
interesting you just speaking about some
of the risks that you need to develop an
intuition for when you're live trading
and you've got a really large book I
guess um one of my friends who's a
market maker he recounted a time where
um members of his team um just kind of
uh miscalculated the risk and the
potential risk of what it would cost
them in terms of the book for dividend
risk so you know suddenly some some of
the firms um undercut their dividend and
it made a massive difference to their
portfolio just because of how large
their portfolio was and the options that
they were trading with so dividend risk
was a huge sensitivity and that's not
necessarily something that um you know
it's really highlighted in the
mathematical Finance program they're not
talking to you about huge dividend risk
um from a portfolio perspective but when
you're trading really large books little
risks like that that you need to develop
an intuition for and at least be aware
of um they they do matter have you have
you got any examples like that where um
you know these little sensitivities that
maybe aren aren't common to think of
aren't your first order Greeks actually
have heavily impacted a
book uh yeah I mean mean dividend risk
is first of all hilarious to me like
because yeah like you said like I I've
heard so many horror stories about
dividend risk but te it's it's a zero
some games so someone needs to be making
on the other side of that and I've never
heard one person so I don't know that
someone's just really good at it and
really quiet but everything I hear about
divid everyone's La yeah every's getting
blown up I mean um gosh the Dividends
are something uh interest rates was a
big one lately um you know how how do
you model interest rates and in the
money options uh you know some people
kind of figure that out um a little bit
faster than others because we had 0%
interest rates for so long that people
kind of got sloppy there yeah I mean
your your your tiny options are going to
be one of the worst the toughest things
to model because what can happen to
Skuse invols and Curts on large
unexpected moves um your
CO's uh I'm old but your great financial
crisis you know you're got the Spanish
banking crisis I mean so many different
things
um like those things when when a option
is close to zero comes back to life
that's one of the things that you're
your models just not going to get right
um oh another one of my favorite things
that it's a phenomenon in real life that
you could never model is what I call
like puts with call Deltas um so like
this happened to Tesla for a while and
any other GameStop for sure any meme
stock like the stock will actually rally
and the puts will be worth more because
volatility will increase so much than
they were at the beginning of the day so
the stocks up you know 40 bucks and the
puts are worth more like there's no
model in the world that's going to be
able to figure that
out that's comical that that that that
aids itself to the infinite volatility
theorem hey yeah oh man yeah like it's
yeah I guess yeah calls go to underlying
and puts go to strike right uh but it's
uh it's it's phenomenal and like it's
like so like okay I I think I want to
short that but then I want to go down so
like do I even hedge anyway but but like
your model is never going to do that so
trying to
overcome that things like that where
your model is just not going to get it
right there's no mathematics that's
going to do that correctly for I mean I
guess you could have some kind of insane
slide but I think it would break I have
to assume it would
break if you you start having puts in
calls with Deltas that are wrong um but
yeah that's that's a big one um what
else in the treasury market one time
they they changed a deliverable rule so
that that that moved things I won't get
into the ins and outs of that but I mean
there's just a lot of small things that
like you
you you made a good point here you're
you're big Greeks you know you're Vegas
SK Kurt everyone's aware of uh and you
can easily hch that out but the the
little things yeah like your dividend
risk like your row like
your anything uh can really eat you up
sometimes and and that's where it sounds
like having that experienced person on
the desk John you know really really
makes a difference and because they've
they've seen they've seen it before
they've heard horror stories from other
people at other firms um about letting
this stuff go so then it's front of mind
when you have years of experience
whereas I guess for that Junior Trader
who's coming into the role it's not
necessarily front of mind when they're
looking at numbers on a screen and
they're worrying about one thing and one
thing only which is where am I offering
and where I asking no that goes both
ways too um I tell people a lot that I
was I'm I'm pretty good at managing
wrist down but I was a better Traer when
I was younger um because I've just seen
too much now you know like like oh this
could happen this could Happ yeah like
you know you're like if you youve been
only get burned so many times before
Evolution will will change your behavior
um so it's yeah that definitely goes
goes both ways but like it it's good to
have balance on the desk too like
because you you need the people who who
are like this is an opportunity and we
need to push it and then you also need
the person is like okay but let's also
think about what could happen um because
like you can't you can't be totally R
first you're not gonna make any money
and you can't be blind and stupid you're
money so there's there's a balance in
there of course no yeah and I guess um
now we we we don't need to talk about
strategies directly because obviously
everything's um kind of proprietary
between firms but um just in general
like just giving our audience a better
sense of the role of the market maker
and where the opportunity is so if we
just paint that picture as um we you
know you've got 12 market makers on a
particular product and you're looking at
your volatility smile which you know has
a certain structure and then you've got
your term structure which is across your
10 years and you're then trading around
that when other people and um other
Market participants and then moving
around their bids and
ass is the response of the market maker
is the opportunity in the fact that you
have some information that you think
that your volatility curve is correct so
therefore if bids and offers move maybe
further up from that then you may be um
trying to take a position where you're
going to benefit from a decrease in
prices back to back to kind of the mean
volatility curve that you
presume yeah
um and you hit a lot points there they
pretty good uh yeah so like the the V
smile is going to be the big one right
that's that's the one that's pretty
straightforward to model and you it's
really hard to get that wrong um unless
you're in a product like uh has more jum
like a your a doll sare product you're
can experience a lot of targeting such
that like your distributions are not
going to be even but say we have a oil
or a stock
um a non-dividend bay stock um you're
you're those that's going to be your
stuff that holds up more often um term
structure there there's a lot of a lot
of stuff there but like you got to be
careful there you know know if you're
like oh this one month you know say you
have three months that are kind of
decreasing then one month that goes
really high after that you're like oh I
should sell that well like maybe um but
maybe there's something else behind that
maybe there's a presidential election
right to like uh you know trying to try
to figure out that and then yeah like
your shapes and things like that um so I
guess just sticking to the volatility
and maybe hearing more about um that you
know because quantitative modeling
around that um so you've got this smile
which is kind of like your your mean of
the line of your distribution of what
you expect to to happen and um the
distribution around that for all the
different
strikes those distributions kind of they
estimated based off historical
volatility or
forecast volatility or what what they
think realized volatility will be what
are the kind of distributions that are
used to model um you know the likelihood
of of moves around those um different
strikes
yeah so I mean like you can you can kind
of model um your inventory you can kind
of back test uh like the risk of certain
spreads you know say you have a 25 Delta
10 Delta five Delta fly um kind of thing
and you can plug that in and most big
firms have back testers and you could
you know check out the variance on that
and how much you expect to get out of
line and how fast it would mean revert
right so like um one how far you can get
line then two like I guess how fast it
would come back would be two things
you'd really want to consider um but
like and and yeah in general like then
you kind of model that within your
framework if you can um being as generic
as possible here like you you need to
change your values on those things and
sometimes changing your values on very
tight spreads is difficult right like if
I have say it's two years out and it's
two strikes to each other uh they're
going to be insanely correlated right
and like from like a covariance
perspective um but like eventually you
need to put in some kind of risk
parameter there because you don't want
to carry an infinite amount of that risk
um so that's just another thing thing
that's is part of the the cycle uh that
didn't wasn't there 20 years ago I mean
it's probably been there for 15 years
now but no one really B that stuff 20
years ago just because it's um fast
execution these days and and um people
are responding in real time and changing
so so I guess what we're talking about
here is that the fact that if if there
is something that trades on a particular
um you know time time and price as a
particular product then um you know all
other bids and office potentially on
that product could be updated is that
right yeah and and that's the thing
right so like if you don't update you're
going to just keep getting swung at and
like so you need to find a way to change
your Market on on that option on that
spread on that whatever uh and so you
have to figure out some kind of
automated theoretical way to do that
quickly or someone else is going to
figure it out faster and and what you're
saying is someone's moving in response
to what so they're being reactionary
with their V curve and they're updating
their both Cur in real time based on
some other product that's traded if you
don't you're saying that you may be at
the adverse selection of that person
updating their V curve in the fact that
they're buying at the right time because
they know it's going to move in that
direction and makers are going to do the
same thing that and that's one of the
harder things to deal with too is like
if people are changing their values you
have to decide if you want to change
with them or if you are confident in
what you're doing um so you know your
confidence in what you're vending is a
big big big deal like and sometime and
it changes right you know like if I were
making a market in 2010 I don't know it
was it was really pretty slow then um
one thing but if you're making a market
on March of 2020 you know maybe maybe
you're way less confident what you have
going on there and like you're like okay
well I don't want to be on an island
here I don't have an opinion um versus
when you do uh so like that's one of the
trickier things like it'd be really easy
to just have your own values all the
time it'd be really easy to just kind of
track the Market's values but trying to
figure out out when when to do which is
a lot of where uh The Edge comes in oh
that's really interesting I guess and
and also so speaking about those bad
times Maybe So like um in 2020 when the
markets um do get really uncertain can
can a market maker ever remove their
bids and offers so I as far as I can
tell there's primary B market makers and
secondary market makers on products and
primary market makers need to be in
there a certain percentage of time is
that right it's different for every
product um so there are markets where
you have to vend um there are markets
where you don't have to vend uh
generally you want to be in there if you
want to trade but I I have seen markets
where screens just went blank and that's
um depending on what position you have
on it can be very scary or very exciting
uh but yeah I mean in I'll talk about 07
because I was on my own then so um yeah
I mean like when you just start gapping
around or the first time they announced
qe1 I
mean markets just just were gone for a
little while sometimes and then then you
know they come back as everyone kind
figures things out are market makers
allowed to do that are they allowed to
just just disappear their um you know to
take off their their offers and bids and
are there any reprecussions with the um
actual
exchange like like certain ones there
would be you could lose your uh status
uh but with certain markets like you're
allowed to and you know they might call
you um I've been in markets where you
know there there were no markets and so
we got out too because you didn't want
to be the only one out there because
what just happened and they'll call you
and then they'll ask you and please put
your markets back in you know like uh in
general I don't know of anyone who's
really been pun punished um for that and
I'm sure it's happened but I you know in
general people just want to be in there
enough that it doesn't happen a lot but
I I've seen it where they're just gone
or or just insanely wide right like I
mean you could have a certain Market
that's usually a dime wide and
everyone's going to get30 wide like
technically you're in Market but usually
they'll have some kind of minimal width
too yeah yeah I see I see that a lot in
the gas market in Australia um
especially on the physical you'll see um
someone sitting there in the bid and
someone sitting there um on the on the
offer and they're like $3 apart you know
with the mid being nine bucks so you've
got this huge huge uh um discrepancy
between where where you're able to sell
and buy from if you're going to trade
with that guy but then the actual Market
you know is done in small volumes and
they're like 20 cents apart so um yeah
it's it's really interesting to see that
you know it kind of depends what markets
what time and what else is going on that
that limits you know what the bit ass
spread is sure and then like so say you
were the only one in there right you you
might go unlit right so may meaning
you'll still trade but you don't want to
show because people because like you
don't want to this is only thing that's
very different now than then uh when I
started when I started you know you're
in the pit so you have your values and
then everyone has their own values but
they're all basically just yours right
now everyone's vending their their
values so like if I had no idea where to
fit things I could open up a market and
fit a smile to it right so if you're the
only one in there you don't really want
to give if you're confident you don't
want to give away your values there
either too so there's a little games M
up there too so yeah vending do you want
to explain that for our audience oh
sorry this I mean like when we we call
it vending quotes whenever you like
so you know when I'm sending all spreads
and options into the Market we we we say
we're vending quotes then um but it's
basically you you have if you're quoting
30,000 things you have 30,000 bids and
30,000 asss out there and if anyone has
any kind
of uh even mediocre software you know
they can look at those values and fit a
smile to them and like okay well this is
especially at the money right at the
money VA is here uh skew is here Kurt is
here but if I feel confident in my
values I don't necess want to give them
to other people for free if I don't have
to exactly so so what you're saying
saying is some market makers may not may
be delaying updating what they truly
think um to the market until they're
ready to respond yeah right and then
that happens more in crazy times right
so if you tried to do that in normal
Market times you you would just not get
on any trades um the people who are
displaying lit liquidity would get all
the trade so it's you know in in in a
world lit markets where people with
multiple people are are are much better
um for for everybody but but in crazy
times you know like
there's certain
strategy that sounds appropriate oh well
no that's that's really interesting oh
well I think we've covered off um Market
making really well there thank you very
much John um I guess for for um our last
segment you know what advice would you
give um to young people so we've spoken
that the landscape is very very
competitive to get in and um people come
with a lot of programming experience and
um you know maybe through Masters and
phds and they've been working very hard
they're very smart individuals what
differentiates a candidate getting in
and what would you recommend to aspiring
um market
makers great question
um a lot of firms are are looking for
you know good good culture fit meaning
you know people who who want to work in
teams who want to be collaborative um
you know if you're just insanely good
individually that can be good but like
in general you're going to have to work
with other smart people uh so you know
people who can collaborate people who
are looking to work with other people um
people who are passionate about trading
uh for me personally when I interview
people I tend to find that people who
really really love trading are much more
successful than people who don't or you
know I mean when I got into this
industry it was not you know the highest
paid industry in the world um now it it
might be um so you know you get people
who are motivated by different things
but people who actually love trading
tend to be a lot more Su successful um
and so yeah I would just say just
getting getting your hands on anything
you can get on uh that's outside the
realm of like
typical math I mean obviously you have
to be good math you have to be at coding
but if you came in and you're like oh I
checked out all these other websites and
then I researched Market making on my
own or I've been running my own Alpha
strategies on some kind of website or I
do these trading competitions that those
are the people that like get flagged as
like okay this person is really
interesting this is a person you want to
talk to yeah showing an actual industry
sorry interest industry no yeah that's
that's really good advice in terms of
the um I I guess most people maybe
coming in they might want to learn how
to program um what dissemination do you
see in your own role like um obviously
you have you have software developers
who are you know producing the trading
software that you're using to then
execute um these trading strategies on
as the pure Trader and then you know
there is this role in between which is
like the quantitative Trader where they
maybe they're doing research and they're
doing development and they're um coming
up with trading strategies and they're
implementing them in you know maybe a
high level language like python would
you be able to explain maybe the roles
that you think fit under this umbrella
of of quantitative um Trader
quantitative analyst um and then
software engineer and kind of where
people could aim for if they want to be
um at a firm doing Market
making uh sure I mean this goes you even
go further than that
um so guess we'll start as close to the
metal as possible you could have like
your your fpga programmers um that is
one of the fastest growing areas you
know that's basically Hardware
programmable Hardware um that that's as
close to the metal as you can get and
those
are very hard to find these days um
getting easier and you know on top of
that you have like your low latency
people your C C++ kind of stuff um these
are typically you know people people who
work on the systems behind the scenes
the way you communicate with the
exchange um things like that like that's
where you really really need the speed
you know it used to be seconds and now
it's probably Nanos um W yeah so like
that's a an area and then when you get
into like um you know your Quant
developers uh you know that's G be
mostly coding but you have to have some
kind of understanding of actual options
I mean maybe not you're not going to
trade them but you at least understand
what a v smile is you know how it works
like uh uh you know when you're changing
things like your correlations and your
covariances and things like that you're
have to have a basic understanding there
um then yeah on the research side um
these are people who are going to
like create models um create other
strategies um you know the real the the
option specific but very math heavy um
and then I how are they usually coming
from PhD backgrounds or coming out from
Quant programs or other firms uh other
firms always uh but you know mostly
Masters are phds um again but it used to
be bachelors's uh so like the the math
inherently is not that hard it's the
application I mean you need it's not
it's not easy but for the the kind of
people who are applying it's not the
math is not the hard part uh it's
putting it all together um and so those
people will be coding in like a a python
and like a C++ right so like some of
your backend stuff you probably still
need to be fast but you want to be high
level uh languages for quick programming
and understanding and running back tests
and things like that and then your Quant
Traders um will generally
[Music]
be putting together actual trading
strategies um so probably mostly python
on that end um you know higher just
higher level uh but like actual making
trades in the market monitoring
how your trades are doing you're GNA be
doing a lot of lot of monitoring uh
which sounds boring but it's not like
you know there's 10,000 things to keep
an eye on um but yeah but you do need
you need very strong coding skills for
any of these roles uh but obviously the
the level of coding is different at each
at each
station and I guess to um to top that
conversation off for the person who um
really wants to become a market maker
and be the trader be the executor um and
they want to have a career over the next
20 years um like you've had in the
industry what what advice would you give
to
yourself um back then when you're
starting out but with the caveat that
it's now in the today's current
landscape with today's technology and
today's resources for
learning uh I mean phenomenal question
like that's it's it's the biggest
combination of world and maybe it's my
bias because that's the area I'm in um
but you know you need the like if you're
coming in now like you need you you need
coding skills for sure you need um very
basic math like I mean probably maybe
Advanced probability but like it's not
as important to understand the linear
algebra behind the
derivations um but then like you know
you us need to get like you need to get
in there and you need to get excited
about it and you need to get reps um so
you know coming in the door no one's
going to expect you to have any kind of
actual trading experience no one's going
to expect you to have talked to Brokers
or experienced markets but like just ask
like so this would one where I'd say the
biggest thing would be after you get the
job like just asking people around you
like I I had a person just come bother
me every day um you know who's a Quant
is asking questions asking questions
asking questions and now they're one of
the most talented Traders around just
the the desire to learn is is what will
get you there like the passion for it
and if if it's not there then it's not
there but if you really really want it
then just ask people around you and just
immerse yourself in it as much as you
can because it's really hard to get
experience in trading without trading
yeah that's phenomenal advice so being
inquisitive and being the person who
wants to learn and um and I guess that's
there are few and far between when you
see actual true High performers that are
willing to go above and beyond and
continue asking the right questions I
guess um yeah I see it in in my own
industry um people get comfortable don't
they yeah I mean there's you know you
bring in a a bunch of new people there's
always just a few who who really really
want it um and they're generally very
successful and you know everyone's got
their own thing it's not for everybody
you know it's it's a very demanding job
but yeah like you can really
differentiate Yourself by just caring
and asking questions and wanting to
learn as much as you can that's
excellent oh well thank you very much
John um that's really invaluable advice
in the last piece we because we spoke
about it before um you did recommend um
a couple of books um had a couple of
book recommendations for people who who
want to become well-versed in the
options and Market making um space What
would those be um and who would you
recommend them to oh man basic level uh
Sheldon nberg um option volatil
impressing is the Bible for Market
making uh it's you know it's very basic
but it's a lot like we said it's one of
those things like there's not a lot of
books out there on this stuff so you
know he he'll teach you the the the
basics there uh Hall um is amazing yeah
yeah it's really really good and then I
mean honestly if you're really into it
um
just books on like the the history um
you know you're God what's the long-term
capital book it's uh oh genius failed um
the new Jim Simons bio is pretty good uh
book quants like just for like learning
how it all came up is kind of
interesting and
then trying to think of other specific
Market making books like those are the
really good ones for the math and then
you kind of want like the story to go
with it yeah that that's a really
interesting perspective um John yeah I
guess you know you've been around for 20
years so you've you've seen these things
develop but um I guess for people who
are starting now and going to start
their Journey their 20y year and plus
Journey um the the history is probably
often you know it's it's a nice um part
that actually assists in your learning
development and understanding why things
are the way they are and and it's
incredibly interesting to see like some
of the most successful firms today how
close they came to closing down like the
number of firms that are are gigantic
today that that have came within a hair
of failing is staggering uh so you know
it's it's always interesting especially
from the Quant perspective to realize
that you know you know you live in a
world of of models and normal
distributions and and that's just
sometimes that doesn't work uh so it's
good for like just kind of having the
back of your head like you need to model
things you need to take risk but like
knowing that it's not always you know a
5 SD move a 10 SD move is going to
happen even though statistically it
never you know like uh that things like
that are very interesting no that's
excellent hey y to to leave um the
viewers um maybe in ad admiration but um
also to to kind of get them excited
about why they would invest their life
into trading obviously it can be a very
lucrative career would you be willing to
say kind of um what the you know minimum
salary that you've kind of seen in the
industry for someone who's first
starting out all the way into the
opportunities for for people to maybe
develop their own um algorithm and then
get percentage and bonus um off off
those when they implemented um what's
kind of the range of salaries and what
are the opportunities there oh man it's
it's it's a gigantic range um so yeah
like I've been around some I know a lot
of different people at a lot of
different companies I mean like
you it's all it's all six figures start
but like I mean at a market making firm
now getting 300 out of school is not
unreasonable um certain firms would pay
more than that um and then like actual
trading I mean it depends on how you do
it it right uh but you can make much
more than that if you go the percentage
route you can make much more or much
less than that but like the and and who
knows right trading is bound to slow
down at some point but the the money is
definitely there right
now because the opportunity and the
volatility is there he yeah exactly and
the volumes are there and like you know
you've seen like the the retail flows
are getting bigger and like it it maybe
it'll come May it'll go away but like
the access to markets is a lot easier so
more people are doing it you have
interest rate volatility now so people
are actually you know kind of trying to
get in there and hedge a little bit um
you know no one really has an interest
in trading interest rates if interest
rates are zero but now you know Banks
actual hedgers mortgage companies things
like that are in there um but the yeah
the the arms race for talent right now
is is is insane so like the the the
money can be very real from day one so
firms are willing to pay for if Talent
oh yeah no it's like I mean I I can tell
you that when I started I think I made
40 Grand and had to do a lot of coffee
running um the industry is no longer
like that uh you know you can make 10
times that uh your first day and and
also like the people are treated
differently you know they're like people
have a no one's I mean so you work in
physical gas so you've heard the yelling
and screaming things like that like I
used to get just everyone in the pit
just yelling screaming yelling screaming
now people are kind of like looking to
develop people you know there's more of
an active actively developing the talent
now um it's a more mature industry
uh so the opportunities are very
different and then you have to get like
it used to be you had to clerk for or
two years or whatever kind of work your
way up now people will just go to
another firm uh if you do that so you
know people are getting opportunities
sooner too it's a very good time to be
is it's a very difficult time to get in
the industry uh but it's a very good
time to get into the industry a
difficult time to get in because of the
competition and it's a good time to be
in it to to be paid and to have a have a
lifelong of fun learning how to tried
yeah I think I mean I think I saw 70,000
people or something applied for Citadel
and Citadel Securities internships like
I
mean I I can't imagine well was probably
just a baby when I got started but you
know it's probably a thousand people you
know so like you said it's it's it's
hard it's incredibly hard and and you
asked really good questions on how to
differentiate yourself and uh I think
that's smart I mean you're going to have
to have the the academics to get there
too but like once you get there how can
you differentiate yourself and it's
probably just love of trading and and
any trading experience that you can make
for yourself through personal accounts
or through trading competitions and
things like that well John that that is
invaluable advice in from someone who
has had 20 years experience in the
market making industry so thank you very
much for coming on to the podcast um any
final
wordss no I mean uh uh you know maybe I
the industry is constantly changing so
maybe a year from now we we can do this
again we can talk about all the things
that have changed but like just the yeah
you know what I do uh
know that this industry changes so fast
um this actually has bitten me a couple
times in my career you become really
successful and you you know kind of like
rest on your laurels uh but
like if you're not constantly innovating
constantly changing you get left behind
so fast so just always always always be
pushing always be
curious if you hear something about a
new way of doing things don't
immediately brush it aside you know ask
more questions because that's happened
to me a few times like oh these these
doing this now I'm like oh that's silly
we don't need to do that and then two
years later now you're two years behind
and you really wish that like you had
put in the research there because these
aren't things you can do overnight um
especially from a technology perspective
just know that like if you get in this
industry it's going to be totally
different five years from from now and
it's gonna be completely different five
years from then like it's it's going to
keep getting crazier and crazier and so
you're have to keep uh keep at it and
keep updating your your skill set so the
learning isn't done after University no
I think that's the learning is never
done
oh well thank you very much again for
coming on John and um and we yeah
hopefully get to speak to you in a
year's time and maybe do a face to face
yeah thanks for having
[Music]
me